<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/" xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/" version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title>Red Box</title>
		<atom:link href="http://www.thetimes.co.uk/redbox/feed?asdadad" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
		<link>http://www.thetimes.co.uk/redbox</link>
		<description>Red Box</description>
		<lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 13:41:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
		<language>en-US</language>
		<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
		<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
		<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=4.2.4</generator>
		<item>
			<title>Cameron’s readiness to be flexible on benefits reflects the political realities</title>
			<link>http://www.thetimes.co.uk/redbox/topic/the-europe-question/camerons-readiness-to-be-flexible-on-benefits-reflects-the-political-realities</link>
			<comments>http://www.thetimes.co.uk/redbox/topic/the-europe-question/camerons-readiness-to-be-flexible-on-benefits-reflects-the-political-realities#comments</comments>
			<pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2015 13:41:28 +0000</pubDate>
			<dc:creator><![CDATA[federica cocco]]></dc:creator>
			<category><![CDATA[]]></category>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">http://redbox-cma.thetimes.co.uk/redbox/?p=12628</guid>
			<description><![CDATA[It did not take Brussels long to tell David Cameron that his most important objective in his reform negotiations was going to be a problem.His call for restrictions on the right of EU migrants to claim benefits in Britain was &#8220;highly problematic&#8221;, it said.And Cameron himself, recognising that he is asking for more than many [&#8230;]]]></description>
			<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It did not take Brussels long to tell David Cameron that his most important objective in his reform negotiations was going to be a problem.</span><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">His call for restrictions on the right of EU migrants to claim benefits in Britain was &ldquo;highly problematic&rdquo;, it said.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">And Cameron himself, recognising that he is asking for more than many countries like Poland will feel able to give, couched that demand in flexible words.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In his letter to Donald Tusk, the European Council president, he suggested that bringing fairness to the immigration system was a &ldquo;shared challenge&rdquo;.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But he hinted that he may be willing to make concessions on the key issue of a four-year bar on access to in-work benefits and housing.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&ldquo;We have proposed that people coming to Britain from the EU must live here and contribute for four years before they qualify for in-work benefits or social housing, and that we should end the practice of sending child benefit overseas,&rdquo; Cameron said earlier.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But he told Tusk: &ldquo;I understand how difficult some of these issues are for other members states and I look forward to discussing these proposals further so we can find a solution that deals with the issue.&rdquo;</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In a speech earlier he said he was &ldquo;open to different ways of dealing with this issue&rdquo;.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If that sounded like a downgrading of earlier pledges it probably was.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cameron made plain that immigration was at the forefront of his mission, while laying out his other demands &ndash; an exemption from the commitment to &ldquo;ever closer union&rdquo;, protection from eurozone integration and improvements in competitiveness.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the letter, he said he hoped to to get an agreement at the &ldquo;earliest possible opportunity&rdquo; but the &ldquo;priority is to get the substance right&rdquo;.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cameron said he was calling for a &ldquo;clear, legally binding and irreversible agreement to end Britain&rsquo;s obligation to work towards an ever-closer union&rdquo;.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&ldquo;That will mean that Britain can never be entangled in a political union against our will or be drawn into any kind of United States of Europe,&rdquo; he said.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">He also urged more powers for national parliaments &ndash; although he stopped short of demanding a &ldquo;red card&rdquo; system that would have given MPs a veto over EU legislation, acknowledging that would cause &ldquo;gridlock&rdquo;.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&ldquo;We want to see a new arrangement where groups of national parliaments can come together and reject European laws which are not in their national interest,&rdquo; he said.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The commission&rsquo;s reaction was predictable if rather swifter than it needed to be. Within minutes of the letter being published a spokesman said: &ldquo;</span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Prima facie we see a number of elements which appear to be feasible, like finding ways to increase the role of national parliaments, some issues which are difficult, like ever closer union and relations between the euro ins and outs, and some things which are highly problematic as they touch upon the fundamental freedoms of the internal market. Direct discrimination between EU citizens clearly falls into this last category.</span></i><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">&rdquo;</span></i></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cameron is finding it hard to get over the message that if he fails, he may campaign to pull out. Most MPs believe that Brussels in the end will give him enough to campaign to stay in, even though he keeps saying that &ldquo;nothing is ruled out&rdquo;.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That may explain his caution over the four-year plan. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Conservative manifesto states: &ldquo;We will insist that EU migrants who want to claim tax credits and child benefit must live here and</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">contribute to our country for a minimum of four years.&rdquo; But Downing Street briefings today, and Cameron&rsquo;s direct offer of flexibility to Tusk, suggests that he may settle for something less, provided he can show that what he is doing will sharply reduce migration. He may have no choice but to accept a lesser deal and then hail it as achieving his original objective.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Tusk will now begin bilateral consultations with member states on the British demands before a summit in Brussels in mid-December.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As *The Times* revealed on Monday, Cameron would love to be in a position to call a referendum as early as next June if he gets a deal.</span></p><p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But for at least two reasons that may prove optimistic. First, the EU may not be ready to give him the outcome he needs. Second, he may need the negotiations to drag on much longer than that to prove he has got something worthwhile.</span></p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://www.thetimes.co.uk/redbox/topic/the-europe-question/camerons-readiness-to-be-flexible-on-benefits-reflects-the-political-realities/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
